Guide to the Gulick Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Gulick Family Papers
1840-1964
RG 299
Yale University Divinity School Library
6.5
16 boxes
The Gulick Family Papers, 1840-1964, primarily document the scientific and missionary life of John Thomas Gulick (1833-1923) in Japan and China and the scientific career of his son Addison Gulick who was Professor of Chemistry at the University of Missouri from 1912 to 1952.
Gulick family
Biographical / Historical
John T. Gulick was born in Waimea, Hawaii in 1832 and died in Honolulu in 1923. He was a Congregational minister and missionary to Japan and China. He was educated at Williams College (1859) and Union Theological Seminary (1861). His life is a very colorful one ranging from gold miner in 1849 to evolutionary scientist.
In the area of science, John T. Gulick was very well known and respected. He published in such well known periodicals as Nature and Journal of the Linnean Society. He is credited for converting George Romanes, a prominent evolutionist of the 19th century, to Christianity. His best known scientific theory is that of evolutionary divergence through the influence of segregation. Gulick was drawn to the area of evolutionary science through his collection of a species known as Achatinellidae.
In the area of Christian missions, he was also quite well known. He was raised in a missionary family and his father, Peter Johnson Gulick, was one of the first missionaries to Hawaii. After graduating from Union, John Gulick went to Japan in 1862 in order to convince the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions to begin work there. In 1864 the ABCFM sent John to Peking and then to Kalgan, China where he stayed until 1875. From there he went to Kobe and Osaka Japan where he remained until 1899.
His first wife, Emily, died in 1875 and he did not remarry until 1880 at which time he married Frances A. Stevens. In 1906, John Gulick returned to Hawaii and there he died in 1923 at the advanced age of 91.
Addison Gulick, the son of John Gulick and his second wife Frances, was also a prominent man of science. Addison spent the largest part of his career as a professor of Chemistry at the University of Missouri (1912-1952). Addison was born in Osaka in 1882. He received his BA from Oberlin and his Ph.D. from the University of Wurttsburg in Germany. Addison married Margaret Buckingham. Despite his missionary background, Addison was an atheist and did not have much love for the missionary movement. Nevertheless, Addison was very proud of his father and wrote a biography of him in the 1930's.
Scope and Contents
The Gulick Family Papers, 1840-1964, primarily document the missionary life of John Thomas Gulick and the scientific career of Addison Gulick. In addition, there are materials from Peter Johnson Gulick (John's Father), Fannie Hinckley Thomas Gulick, Emily Gulick, Orramel H. Gulick, Julia A. E. Gulick and Frances A. S. Gulick.
Much of the material is comprised of personal correspondence between family and friends but much of these letters document the history of 19th century missionary work in China, Japan and Hawaii. In addition to the personal letters are many publications, poems, sermons, collected publications, copies of letters and personal effects. Addison Gulick was not a missionary but a prominent scientist at the University of Missouri. His major contribution to this collection is a biography of his father John Thomas Gulick. Also, Addison Gulick should be credited for his preservation efforts of many letters that John T. Gulick wrote to prominent evolutionary scientists of the 19th century - most notable are George Romanes and Charles Darwin. The original letters are not part of this collection but many copies have been included. Also, Addison Gulick was responsible for making sure that John T. Gulick's writings and shell collection were placed into the hands of museums and depositories for preservation and research and the locations of these are documented throughout Addison's papers.
Generally, the collection is personal in nature and documents the private lives of the Gulick family. However, many of the Gulicks had prominent public lives and so the personal nature of the material offers a private view of their many public accomplishments. The bulk of the papers originate before 1923, which is the year that John T. Gulick died. After this date, the collection primarily reflects the life of Addison Gulick.
Conditions Governing Access
The material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School, 2017
Custodial History
Donated to Andover Newton Theological School by Mary Gulick. 1997
Arrangement
Series I. Gulick Family Letters and Writings
Series II. Addison Gulick Papers
Series III. John T. Gulick Papers
Missions -- Japan; Missions -- China; Natural selection; Gulick family; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923; Gulick, Addison, 1882-
- Gulick Family Letters and Writings, Series I
  - Letters, 1840-1907 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1908-1909 June (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1909 July - 1919 (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1920–1964 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence between Addison Gulick and Romanes family, 1960–1961 (Box 4)
  - Undated letters, No date
  - Letters of Peter Johnson Gulick (Copies), 1840–1876 (Box 5)
  - Letters of Fannie Hinckley Thomas Gulick (Copies), 1849–1867 (Box 5)
  - Letters of Emily Gulick (Copies), 1871–1875 (Box 5)
  - Letters of Francis A.S. Gulick (Copies), 1876-1898, 1925 (Box 5)
  - Letters and writings of Robert, Julia, Thomas and Orramel H. Gulick (Copies), No date (Box 5)
  - Published writings of Orramel H., Julia, Francis and Annie Gulick, 1910–1928 (Box 5)
- Addison Gulick Papers, Series II
  - Professional Writings
    - Writings, 1904-1922, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Writings, 1932–1965 (Box 6)
    - Manuscripts, No date (Box 6)
    - "The Koloa House" – Picture Drawn by Addison Gulick, No date (Box 6)
    - Index of Genera…used by John T. Gulick, No date (Box 6)
    - Memoranda concerning the scientific work of John T. Gulick, No date (Box 6)
    - "Collection of Achatinella," of John T. Gulick (collected by Addison Gulick - includes correspondence), No date (Box 6)
  - Files of Addison Gulick
    Scope and Contents
    Include school notes, papers, collected publications,., etc.
    - "Memoranda Relative to the John T. Gulick Land Snail Collection and Biography" (Box 7)
    - "JTG, Flower, Darwin, Agassiz Correspondence" (Box 7)
    - "Locations of Gulick-Romanes Transcripts" (Box 7)
    - "History of Isolation - Evolutionary Theory" (Box 7)
    - "Re: Japan-America Centennial Award to FASG" (Box 7)
    - "Radical Critical Bibliography, Notes On" (Box 7)
    - "Book Review 'Birth of the Gospel'" (Box 7)
    - "A.G. Abstracts 1948 - From For. Lang. Journs. For Excerpta Medica" (Box 7)
    - "Miscellaneous from the Files of Addison Gulick" (Box 7)
    - Publications collected by Addison Gulick, circa 1905-1957 (Box 7)
    - Class lecture notes and miscellaneous manuscripts of Addison Gulick (presumably) (Box 7)
    - Files under title of "Letters RE: W.B. Smith Works" (Box 8)
      See original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton, for full list of folder titles.
    - Files under title of "W.B. Smith - 'Birth'" (Box 9)
    - Additional files of Addison Gulick (various topics) (Box 9)
  - Personal Items and Memorabilia of Addison Gulick
    - "Life History Album" – Includes Pamphlet on Eugenics (Box 9)
    - Dated Correspondence/Nostalgia (Box 9)
    - Undated Correspondence/Nostalgia (Box 9)
    - Photographs of Addison and Mrs. Addison Gulick (Box 9)
    - Emeritus Ribbons (Box 9)
    - Emeritus Certificate (Box 9)
- John T. Gulick Papers, Series III
  - Poetry and prose
    - Letters concerning poetry of John T. Gulick, 1880–1914 (Box 10)
    - Published poems of John T. Gulick, 1859–1910 (Box 10)
    - "A Tour Through the North Hills" (includes correspondence about its publication), 1859 (Box 10)
    - "Essays, Sketches and Jottings of John T. Gulick" (copies), 1853-1885, no date (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous prose of John T. Gulick (Box 10)
  - Publications
    - Published writings of John T. Gulick, 1857–1885 (Box 10)
    - Published writings of John T. Gulick, 1887-1914, 1924 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence
    All letters are copies
    - Letters from and to John T. Gulick, 1849–1915 (Box 11)
    - Letters to John T. Gulick re. his 80th birthday, 1912 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. John T. Gulick and Rufus Anderson & N.G. Clark, 1864–1875 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence between John T. Gulick and other scientists, 1872–1897 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence between John T. Gulick and George Romanes, Charles Darwin, A. R. Wallace, W. Percy Sladen, Henri de Varigny, J. Fletcher Moutlon, et al., 1887–1905 (Box 11)
  - Additional papers
    - Manuscripts of John T. Gulick (including bibliography), Mostly undated (Box 12)
    - "Letter Book" – Manuscript letters of John T. Gulick (source material for many of the copied letters) (Box 12)
    - Notes on books read, 1851–1859 (Box 12)
    - Papers and scrapbook found among the works of John T. Gulick (Box 12)
    - Publications collected by John T. Gulick, 1888–1923 (Box 12)
    - Journal of John T. Gulick (copies), 1841–1862 (Box 13)
    - Other autobiographical writings of John T. Gulick (Box 13)
    - Journal John T. Gulick - edited by Addison Gulick "as of 1926" (copies) - chapters 1-10 (Box 14)
    - Journal of John T. Gulick - edited by Addison Gulick "as of 1926" (copies) - chapters 11-end (Box 15)
    - Letters and reviews re. biography of John T. Gulick, "John Thomas Gulick: Evolutionist and Missionary" (Box 16)
    - 3 copies of biography (Box 16)